A Guide to the Papers of Anne Spencer and the Spencer Family, 1829, 1864-2007
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Anne Spencer and the Spencer Family, 1829, 1864-2007
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
14204
4175 items, 22 Hollinger boxes, ca. 9 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Anne Spencer were purchased from the Anne Spencer House and Garden Museum, Lynchburg, Virginia, by the University of Virginia Library on March 10, 2008.
Biographical/Historical Information
Anne Bethel Spencer was born an only child in Henry County, Virginia, on February 6, 1882, to Joel Cephus Bannister (1862-?) of Henry County, Virginia, and Sarah Louise Scales (1866-?) of Patrick County, Virginia. Sometime around 1883, the family moved to Martinsville, Virginia, where Joel opened a saloon. Sarah had relatives in Bramwell, West Virginia, and she moved there in either 1887 or 1888 to work in the Blue Stone Inn. Soon Anne was able to join her mother in Bramwell, where she lived with the family of the local barber, William T. Dixie and his wife, Willie Belle. In September 1893, Annie moved to Lynchburg, Virginia, at the age of eleven in order to attend Virginia Seminary for her education. She was registered there as Annie Bethel Scales in September 1893.
Anne Spencer graduated on May 8, 1899, and gave the valedictory speech during the ceremony held at Diamond Hill Baptist Church, Lynchburg. Following graduation Annie began teaching second grade in West Virginia, near Bramwell. She and Edward A. Spencer (1876-1964) were married on May 15, [1901] by the Reverend Frank Marshall in Bramwell, West Virginia, at the home of her friends, William T. and Willie Belle Dixie, and set up housekeeping in Lynchburg, Virginia. They had three children, Bethel Calloway, Alroy Sarah, and Chauncey Edward Spencer, and a fourth child who died shortly after birth with diphtheria.
Working with NAACP secretary James Weldon Johnson, she helped co-found the Lynchburg chapter of the NAACP in 1918. It was also Johnson who discovered her poetry and was instrumental in getting her first published poem, "Before the Feast of Shushan" to the public. It was published in The Crisis in February 1920. The poetry of Anne Spencer can be found in some of the period's most prestigious anthologies, including The Book of American Negro Poetry (James Weldon Johnson); Negro Poets and Their Poems (Robert T. Kelin); American Poetry Since 1900 (Louis Untermeyer); The New Negro (Alain Locke); Caroling Dusk (Countee Cullen); and The Poetry of the Negro, 1746-1949 (Langston Hughes and Arna Bontemps). Spencer is recognized as a part of the Harlem Renaissance literary movement not only because of her published poetry but her friendships with many of the other African-American writers of the time.
Anne Spencer became the librarian at the Dunbar High School in Lynchburg and worked there from about 1924 until 1946. She lived most of her adult life in Lynchburg, Virginia, chiefly at 1313 Pierce Street, where she hosted many literary and civil rights figures in her home during their visits to her area.
Scope and Content
The papers of Anne Spencer (1882-1975) and family, 1829, and ca. 1864-2007, and undated, 4,175 items (22 Hollinger boxes, ca. 9 linear feet) consist of correspondence, photographs, manuscripts and notebooks of poetry, short stories, articles, and prose works, often fragmentary in nature and undated, financial and legal papers and volumes, and topical files.
The collection contains manuscript poems, ideas for poems, and articles by Spencer, including an autobiographical piece, 1956, sent to Lee Greene, typescript copies of some of her poems by Greene, and articles possibly written for a column in the Pittsburgh Courier, but never published. Prose manuscripts include "Bastion at Newark," "Chattel slavery or why I dislike Booker T," "Comments about herself spoken to Ben W. Fuson," "Dear children," "In the thicket" [regarding a short story by James Weldon Johnson], "LeRoi meets Lincoln," and "Virginia as Narcissus."
Poetry manuscripts include "Any wife to any husband," "Ascetic," "At the carnival," "Before the feast of Shushan," "Black man o' mine," "Creed," "Dunbar," "Epitome," "For E.A.S.," "Failure," "For Jim, Easter Eve" [also titled "To James Weldon Johnson Easter Eve (1938-1948)]," "Grapes: Still-Life," "He said," "I have a friend," "Innocence," "Lady, lady," "Lemming: O Sweden," "Letter to my Sister," "Liability," "Lines to a Nasturtium," "Life-long, poor Browning," "Luther P. Jackson," "1975," "Neighbors," "Po' little lib," "Questing," "Requiem," "Rime for the Christmas baby," "The Sévignés," "Substitution," "Terrence, Terrence," "Translation," "White things," and "The Wife-woman." There are also drafts and fragments of unfinished poems she constantly revised particularly "Big Ditch and the River," "A Dream of John Brown: on his return trip home."
Themes and topics in untitled manuscripts and fragments include books and literature; family; African Americans, slavery, segregation, and civil rights; gardening and nature; historical and contemporary events and figures; politics and government particularly in Virginia; and religion.
Correspondence of Anne Spencer is chiefly with and about family, friends, fellow poets and anthologizers. Of interest are letters from Sterling A. Brown, Countee Cullen, Victor Daly, Arthur P. Davis, W.E.B. du Bois, Helen G. Edmonds, Murrell Edmunds, Ben Fuson, J. Lee Greene, Langston Hughes, Altona Trent Johns, Georgia Douglas Johnson, Grace Johnson, James Weldon Johnson, Charles S. Johnson, Alain LeRoy Locke, Harry Meacham, H. L. Mencken (copy), Amaza Meredith, Clarence Muse, Francis Coleman Rosenberger, Frank Silvera, Idella Purnell [Stone], Howard Thurman, and Carl Van Vechten, concerning her poetry and their own work. There are also letters to Andres Burris and to Cleveland Amory re Ellen Glasgow, James Branch Cabell and racism.
Topics of interest in the correspondence include Langston Hughes, Adam Clayton Powell, Claude McKay, and William Raspberry, Jim Crow laws and segregation, and the Spencer family. There are many brief comments on people in the news and current events including the Democratic Presidential Convention of 1948 and the Republican Convention of 1952.
There are numerous photographs of family and friends including Guy Bluford, Celinda Wright Humbles, Joe Louis, Amaza Meredith, Clarence Muse, and Ulysses S. Grant Patterson, as well as a Tuskegee Airmen convention and the faculty of the Virginia Theological Seminary.
Financial and legal papers chiefly concern the Lynchburg, Virginia, property management business, tax business and chicken business of Edward Spencer. Many of his business ledgers were later reused by his widow for jotting down her poetry ideas. Also present is an 1829 New Hampshire deed, an 1863 will, and the wills of Anne and her husband.
Miscellaneous material includes material pertinent to an Anne Spencer Poetry Contest, the Friends of the Anne Spencer Memorial Foundation and the Virginia Landmarks Register inclusion for the Anne Spencer House as well as facsimiles of historic African American and historic broadsides; invitations; clippings; programs; a few papers concerning Chauncey Spencer, a Tuskeegee Airman, including a blueprint for a hangar at Dothan, Ala.; mimeograph copies of poetry by Gerald William Barrax; and a rough draft of "Searching for Anne Spencer" by Pat Doyle.
Arrangement
The papers of Anne Spencer arrived with almost no discernible order. The current order was imposed by the processor. The papers are arranged in five series: Series I: Correspondence (Boxes 1-6); Series II: Photographs (Boxes 7-9); Series III: Financial and Legal Papers and Volumes (Boxes 9-13); Series IV: Topical Files (Boxes 13-17); and Series V: Manuscripts, both individual and in notebooks (Boxes 17-22).
Series V is also subdivided into several subseries: Subseries A: Manuscripts with a title; Subseries B: Manuscripts arranged by beginning line; Subseries C: Topical Manuscripts with no titles, arranged by subject; Subseries D: Dated Notebooks; Subseries E: Undated Notebooks; and Subseries F: Poems and Other.
Correspondence is summarized at the folder level, and while all identified correspondents are listed, not all letters are described individually. When possible, negatives have been placed in the same folder with their photographs.
Poems and manuscripts with titles have their own folder and are listed separately. Other manuscripts are arranged by the apparent topic when it can be determined. Some designations of topics by the processor are very subjective and often several different topics can be found within a single manuscript. Dated notebooks are described first, followed by the undated notebooks. Undated notebooks have been assigned an alphabet designation to keep them distinct in the guide.
Contents List
- Correspondence (Box 1-6)
  - Correspondence - A: including Robert A. Abernathy; Joanne K. Abrams; [Martha?] Rivers Adams, Virginia M. Alexander, M.D.; Atlanta University, School of Library Science, Virginia Lacy Jones1933-1974 (Box-folder 1:1))
  - Correspondence - B: including Frances and [Johnston Bahner?]; Judge Alfred Dickinson Barksdale (excusing Anne Spencer from jury duty); Ralph Barnette (asks for a holograph copy of "The Wife-Woman"); Winston Bell; N.F. and C.C. Berry; Maggie N. Bickerstaff; Bess Bondurant; Roberta Bosley, requests permission from Spencer to use her poem written to Mr. Johnson [For Jim, Easter Eve] during a memorial service for Johnson (May 27, 1940); Hortense Braswell; Camilla E. Brightwell; Nellie Frances Tiline Adams Brodis; G.H. Brooks; Marie Joe Brown; Elizabeth Burnette; Andrew Burris (with untitled poem attached to September 24, 1945); and the Butlers1933-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 1:2))
  - Correspondence - Daisy and Sterling A. Brown (1901-1989), chiefly Christmas cards, but also includes two early letters (undated) from Sterling Brown, recounting his activities, his reading, and poems he has written; one undated letter was written while he was teaching at Lincoln University, Missouri, between 1927 and 1929, which mentions his plans to enter "Big Boy" in the Nation poetry contest; and a letter, February 23, 1977, to Chauncey Spencer declining to attend the dedication ceremonies for the Anne Spencer House because of illness but enclosing a statement of their love, respect, and admiration for Anne Spencer to the Board of Directors of the Friends of Anne Spencer Memorial Foundation. One of Brown's poems, "To a Certain Lady, In Her Garden" was written to pay tribute to Anne Spencer. Includes a draft of an undated letter from Anne Spencer to Brown, with the note "A poet can easily tell a lie but gets the heeby-jeebies if he has to face one."1958-1977, n.d. (Box-folder 1:3))
  - Correspondence - C: including [Evert?] Calloway; J.M. Campbell, Jones Memorial Library; L. Carey; Jean Cason; Arthur P. Chippey; [Katharene W. Chippey ?], postcards signed "Kitty"; Rosa Lee Christian; Louise E. Coleman, Committee for Virginia of the Southern Conference for Human Welfare; and Mary M. Councell, concerning Spencer's permission to use the biographical sketch about her written by Murrell Edmunds (March 22, 1957, August 27, 1958)1939-1970 (Box-folder 1:4))
  - Correspondence - Countee Cullen, reminds Spencer of the poem she promised him for the special issue of Palms published October 1926 (December 3, 1925); doesn't know "Wife-Woman" and asks her to send a copy of it with her other material (November 24, 1926); says her biographical notice was just the sort of thing he wanted for his anthology (May 26, 1927); thanks her for her two poems, wants to keep both of them, and quotes Alice Dunbar Nelson's comments about Spencer from her review of Caroling Dusk (November 17, 1927); and comments "The inclusion of your poem in Braithwaite's anthology for this year, is another happy evidence that this veteran anthologist is as discerning and as appreciative as ever" (February 1, 1928).1925-1928 (Box-folder 1:5))
  - Correspondence - D: Victor Daly (author of Not Only War), Arthur P. Davis (1904-1996), Howard University, writes about using Spencer's poetry in his anthology, The Negro Caravan (May 17, 1941) and later asks permission to reprint her poems, hoping to add a new one to the anthology (July 5, 1969); Mary Davis, briefly mentions meeting Maria Cole, wife of Nat King Cole (April 8, 1965) and the papal visit of Pope Paul VI (October 5, 1965); Lucille T. Dickerson, Jones Memorial Library; E.W. Dickerson about real estate (March 7, 1941); post card to Mrs. Willie Dixie from [Anne Spencer] announcing birth of a fine boy [November 6, 1906]; and [Miss?] Zita Dresner, requesting a list of her publications or copies of both published and unpublished works, and noting that she has devoted a section of her course on women writers of the Harlem Renaissance to Spencer (November 3, 1972). Anne Spencer has penciled a draft of a reply on the back of the letter, which says it was not sent.1934-1972 (Box-folder 1:6))
  - Correspondence - W.E.B. Du Bois, asks her for some poems for publication in The Crisis, her entry into their contest, and for a photograph of her home and garden (March 31, 1926); a typed copy of his letter to Ruth L. Bartholomaw about Ann Spencer (May 9, 1928); also present are two cards, one announcing the death of Nina Gomer Du Bois on June 26, 1950, and the second announcing the address of Du Bois and Shirley Graham, September 1, [1951?]1926-1928, 1950-51 (Box-folder 1:7))
  - Correspondence - E: Helen G. Edmonds (1911-1995), mentions review of her book [The Negro and Fusion Politics in North Carolina, 1894-1901 ?] (October 10, 1951), describes her trip across the ocean on the Queen Mary to Heidelberg, Germany, with the "stiff" attitude of the Americans towards her (September 24, 1954), and a card telling Spencer to watch television Monday evening, "President Eisenhower will be on. I hope I do O.K." (October 7, 1960); Murrell Edmunds discusses his personal difficulties of the past year, saying "I presume you have heard of my acute psychic upheaval of last Spring; and now I am in New Orleans for an indefinite period with my elder brother" and ironically shares some of his recent successes (December 11, 1934) and sends a copy of his book Behold, Thy Brother (December 18, 1950), has received a copy of her poem "1975" through Lee Greene, which he praises highly (December 27, 1974). There is also a draft of a letter from Anne Spencer to Edmunds, thanking him for his "precious packet of love and valiant friendship and mentioning Lee Greene and her poem "1975" (1974); James C. Evans, regrets hearing about the illness, then death of Edward A. Spencer (May 8 and June 3, 1964); John B. Evans, Jr.; Mary L. Evans; and Theresa G. Evans (1908-1999), wife of William L. Evans, co-founder of the Buffalo Urban League, and possible niece of Ed and Anne Spencer1934-1974 (Box-folder 1:8))
  - Correspondence - F: Fannie Fairfax; Eleazar Ferguson; John and Ophelia Fisher; Bertinus Fleshman; and Mary Fox, Executive Secretary of the League for Industrial Democracy 1929-1967 (Box-folder 1:9))
  - Correspondence - Family, chiefly extended family and grandchildren of Anne and Edward Spencer, including: a letter from son-in-law Robert F. Stevenson, working in a laboratory in the Philippines, mentioning how long he had been married to Bethel (March 1 1948); and letter about a positive experience attending the 1948 Democratic Presidential Convention in Philadelphia with miners, farmers and "regular" people (July 28, 1948).1943-1962 (Box-folder 1:10))
  - Correspondence - Family, chiefly extended family and grandchildren of Anne and Edward Spencer 1963-1976 (Box-folder 1:11))
  - n.d. Correspondence - Family, chiefly extended family and grandchildren of Anne and Edward Spencer (Box-folder 2:1))
  - 1927-1954 Correspondence - Family - Alroy Sarah (Spencer) Long Rivers and Francis Ellis Rivers, daughter and son-in-law of Anne and Edward Spencer, including: discussion of Langston Hughes' speech at a protest meeting in support of Jacques Roumain (1907-1944), a Haitian poet in jail because of his Communist activities [ca. 1934?]; mention of reactions to Langston Hughes's play "Mulatto" on [Broadway?] [October 28, 1935]; copies of Alroy's correspondence with the Virginia State Board of Education about securing aid to pursue more graduate training in psychology (September 19 and 23, 1938); mentions a visit by Sterling Brown, who was lecturing at New York University [November 18, 1938]; comments on the book Black Boy and shares her experience in giving three lectures to the Business and Professional Women's group at the Brooklyn Y.M.C.A. on personality development and relationships while her audience wondered aloud if she was "colored" [March 17, 1945]; discusses her separation and upcoming divorce from Rawley Long [March 4, 1947]; her residence in Reno, Nevada (July 18, 1947); describes one of the homes of heiress Doris Duke (1912-1993) in Nevada [August 10, 1947]; her upcoming marriage to Ellis Rivers [1948?]; a very in-depth analytical letter from Judge Ellis [Rivers] (carbon copy) to Lloyd Kerford, Atchison, Kansas, about the uphill battle of the Republican Party to appeal to the Negro voter after the close of the Convention on July 11, with a document [by Ellis?] "A Resume of the Republican National Convention of 1952 as Affecting the Negro" attached (July 18, 1952); and a paper by Francis Rivers, "Racial Harmony as a Supreme Challenge to the Post-War Generation" (September 11, 1952). (Box-folder 2:2))
  - 1955-1972 Correspondence - Family - Alroy Sarah (Spencer) Long Rivers and Francis Ellis Rivers, daughter and son-in-law of Anne and Edward Spencer, including: Ellis Rivers shares his reaction to the film Something of Value (April 25, 1957); trip to Mexico (August 5, 1961); draft of a letter to the Editor of The Lynchburg News concerning their editorial about Edward Spencer (May 19, 1964); and a highly decorated "letter" to the Rivers from Alex Davis, at the Sagamore, Adirondacks, New York [July 17, 1965]. (Box-folder 2:3))
  - n.d. Correspondence - Family - Alroy Sarah (Spencer) Long Rivers and Francis Ellis Rivers, daughter and son-in-law of Anne and Edward Spencer, including: comments of Walter White about Anne Spencer at a New York library event (n.d.); her work for a candidate in a Congressional race against Adam Clayton Powell (n.d.) (Box-folder 2:4))
  - 1923-1959 Correspondence - Family - Bethel Calloway (Spencer) Stevenson, daughter of Anne and Edward Spencer, including: her reaction to the election of 1954 and television (November 4, 1954). (Box-folder 2:5))
  - 1960-1975, n.d. Correspondence - Family - Bethel Calloway (Spencer) Stevenson, daughter of Anne and Edward Spencer, including: a description of the desolate life in Newark, New Jersey, for minorities (February 12, 1968). (Box-folder 2:6))
  - 1941-1971 Correspondence - Family - Chauncey Spencer and his wife, Anne Howard Spencer, son and daughter-in-law of Anne and Edward Spencer, including: a letter expressing his pride and appreciation for the life and career of Joseph Louis Barrow (June 19, 1946); difficulties with housing in San Bernardino, California, due to inspectors condemning the house to prevent their move into the neighborhood and help from Clarence Muse who sent over some studio carpenters, etc. to help improve the house on the weekends (June 6, 1958 and December 21, 1959); Frank Silvera, actor (1914-1970) trying to reach them and starring in a play reminding him of Chauncey's story (November 29, 1959); and a Clete Roberts (1912-1984) letter (March 28, 1962). (Box-folder 3:1))
  - 1972-1998 Correspondence - Family - Chauncey Spencer and his wife, Anne Howard Spencer, son and daughter-in-law of Anne and Edward Spencer, including the visit of Lee Greene with the family (March 16, 1972); Garnell Stamps postcard about seeing the James Weldon Johnson-Anne Spencer letters at Yale (July 6, 1976); several letters from fans of Who Is Chauncey Spencer? (June 1 and 6, 1976); death of Grace Nail Johnson, with announcement of her death and two letters from Mrs. Ollie Jewel Sims Okala about her service (November 1 and 16, 1976); copy of a letter from Lady Bird Johnson about her visit to Anne Spencer home (May 6, 1977); and a copy of a letter thanking him for the article about his mother and his inclusion in the Smithsonian archives from Lady Bird Johnson (April 8, 1996). (Box-folder 3:2))
  - 1999, n.d. Correspondence - Family - Chauncey Spencer and his wife, Anne Howard Spencer, son and daughter-in-law of Anne and Edward Spencer (Box-folder 3:3))
  - 1950-1976, 1979, n.d. Correspondence - Ben and Daisy Lee Fuson, chiefly Christmas and other newsletters from former Lynchburg College professor and family, one referring to the "moon walk" (September 28, 1969); one letter and a card to Chauncey Spencer, July 23 & October 2, 1976, contains a typed transcript of Anne Spencer's "Comments About Herself, Spoken to Ben W. Fuson" on June 27, 1969. An audiocassette with her comments of same date is also present in the collection. (Box-folder 3:4))
  - 1940-1975 Correspondence - G: Frances M. Gaylison; Eleanor Chippey G[ies?]; R.P. Gifford; T.B. Dalton Gifford; [C?] Scott Goins (Mrs. William F. Goins, Jr.); Frances Greene; Gwendolyn Greene; and Mary Guggenheimer (Box-folder 3:5))
  - 1972-1978 Correspondence - J. Lee Greene and Murrell Edmunds about Edmunds knowledge of Anne Spencer's life and work in Lynchburg, some of which was incorporated into Greene's book (Box-folder 3:6))
  - 1971-1975, n.d. Correspondence - J. Lee Greene and Anne Spencer, which illustrate his interviews and questions used in his biography of Spencer, including: letter designating Lee Greene her literary executor (January 15, 1973); letter discussing her comments about epithets, and referring to Woodrow Wilson and James Branch Cabell (September 4, 1974); a draft of a thank you letter from Anne Spencer (n.d.) and a draft of a letter from her about misplacing his letter and collage, with a couplet for LBJ, a reference to Senator Byrd and the Civil Rights Bill on page three, and a reference to the slaves at Jamestown in 1619 on page four (n.d.) (Box-folder 3:7))
  - 1972-1987 Correspondence - J. Lee Greene concerning Anne Spencer, including: a letter from Francis Coleman Rosenberger (September 30, 1972); Ben W. Fuson, describing circumstances of his meeting Anne Spencer while a professor at Lynchburg College (March 3, 1974); interest of R.P. Gifford in "developing a historical restoration project around her fame and contributions" at 1313 Pierce Street (April 3, 1975); Carrie Allen McCray concerning friendship of her mother, Mary Rice Hayes Allen, with Anne Spencer (November 24, 1987) (Box-folder 3:8))
  - 1976-1982 Correspondence - J. Lee Greene and The Friends of Anne Spencer Memorial Foundation Board, including: the selection of her home as a Virginia Landmark (September 22, 1976); Echoes from the Garden movie project (August 6, 1978); honorarium to Greene for preparing film script (May 14, 1980) (Box-folder 3:9))
  - 1971-1978, n.d. Correspondence - J. Lee Greene and members of Anne Spencer's family, including: a letter from Bethel Stevenson enclosing copies of letters from others interested in talking with Anne Spencer (April 9 and November 8, 1974); a forwarded letter from Harry Meacham and Murrell Edmunds (January 27, 1975); suggested changes or corrections for the biography (April 15, 1975) (Box-folder 4:1))